<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Examination of Sir Ralph Hopton, Sir Iohn Winter, Sir John Stowell with two other knights upon their knees at the barre in the House of Commons the 14 day of this instant October : with the articles of high treason exhibited against them by the House of Commons.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3724</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09523534</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09523534</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38978)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1331:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Examination of Sir Ralph Hopton, Sir Iohn Winter, Sir John Stowell with two other knights upon their knees at the barre in the House of Commons the 14 day of this instant October : with the articles of high treason exhibited against them by the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hopton, Ralph Hopton, --  Baron, 1598-1652.</term>
               <term>Winter, John, --  Sir, 1600?-1673?</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43473:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43473:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EXAMINATION OF Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Winter,</hi> Sir <hi>John Stowell,</hi> with two other Knights, upon their knees at the Barre, in the Houſe of Commons, the 14 day of this inſtant October.</p>
            <p>With the Articles of high Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, exhibited againſt them by the Houſe of COMMONS.</p>
            <figure>
               <q xml:lang="lat">IN DOMINO CONFIDO</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>London, Printed in the yeer 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:43473:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43473:2"/>
            <head>The Examination of Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Winter,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Stowell,</hi> with two other Knights, brought upon their knees at the Barr in the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> the 14. day of this inſtant <hi>October</hi> with the Articles of High Treaſon exhibited againſt them by the Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ryday</hi> being the 14 of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> was Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Winter,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Stowell</hi> with two other Knights, which were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended at Falmouth in the County of Cornwall, by the Earle of Bedfords Forces, brought to the Barr in the Houſe of Commons, and after ſubmiſsion ſeverally made to the Houſe, they were commanded out againe by a Serjeant at Armes, upon which the Houſe falling into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43473:3"/>debate of the offences by them committed in the County of Summerſet-ſhire Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-ſhire and Cornwall againſt the Kings good Subjects. They were unanimouſly voted Delinquents againſt both King and Parliament, after which Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> was againe called to the Barr, and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon theſe queſtions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by what authority or Commiſsion the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> did leavy and cauſe to be leavyed Forces in the County of Summer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-ſhire againſt the expreſſe order and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration publiſhed by authority of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wherefore he endeavoured to put the Commiſsion of Array in execution in that County, it having been declared illegall by the Iudgement of both Houſes of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and in oppoſition to the Ordinance of both Houſes for putting the Militia in execution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By what authority the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> cauſed to be raiſed Horſe, Money and Plate for maintenance of the war begun againſt the Parliament, and ſeizing by force of Armes the goods of divers Gentlemen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43473:3"/>well affected to the Parliaments procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, which refuſed to lend any money or plate, or to ſet forth any Horſe according to his deſires.</p>
            <p>Vpon which, the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> was called to make anſwer to the ſaid que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, who anſwered in brief, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he had done was by authority from Marqueſſe Hartford, the Lord <hi>Seymour</hi> and the Lord <hi>Paulet,</hi> who had received a Commiſsion of Array from His Majeſty, That he was not convinced in his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the illegality of the ſaid Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but by vertue thereof had lawfull po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to put that County into a poſture of Defence.</p>
            <p>For his endeavouring to raiſe money, Horſe and plate for the uſe and ſervice of His Maieſty, it was by vertue of Warrants in His Maieſties Name directed to him for that purpoſe, which he conceived he was bound by his Oath of Allegiance to obey, upon which his anſwers he was againe commanded from the Barr, and the Houſe falling into conſideration and great debate touching the ſame, <hi>una voce</hi> voted theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43473:4"/> 1. That the raiſing of Forces without conſent of both Houſes of Parliament, and marching with the ſame againſt any of his Maieſties Subiects, is actually leavying of war, and hath been by the Lawes of this Land adjudged Treaſon againſt King and Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That for any Member of either of both Houſes to leave their attendance for the ſervice of the State, and privately depart without leave of the Houſe, and ſhall in diſobedience to the Orders and Summons of the ſame refuſe to make his appearance is a high breach of the priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That to endeavour to raiſe or procure any money, Armes or Amunition for the nouriſhing or maintenance of any warre raiſed againſt the State is Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To joyne any Forces ſo raiſed againſt the Lawes of the Land, and Ordinances of Parliament, with any perſons that by both Houſes are declared Traytors, is Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every the aforeſaid Votes, and ought
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43473:4"/>to be proceeded againſt accordingly.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the aforeſaid particulars ſhall be drawne into a charge againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> and a Committee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the perfecting of the ſame, and preſenting it to the Houſe on Munday next.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> ſhall be forthwith committed priſoner to the Tower.</p>
            <p>After which, Sir <hi>Iohn Stowell</hi> and the reſt were called in ſeverally, and after exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation it being put to the queſtion, it was reſolved that the ſaid Knights, firſt for joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and confederating themſelves with Marqueſſe <hi>Hertford,</hi> Lord <hi>Seymour,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Paulet</hi> in the warre againſt the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, who are declared Traytors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For raiſing of Forces joyntly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally in the Counties of Summerſet-ſhire, Dorcheſter, Devon-ſhire and Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, and marching againſt the Forces rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Authority for Parliament, for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing tumultuous and malignant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have endeavoured to diſturbe the peace of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43473:5"/> 3. For refuſing to appeare before the Houſe of Commons upon their Summons as Delinquents, but returning ſleight and diſobedient anſwers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For endeavouring to put the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of Array in execution againſt the Parliament are guilty of high Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Then the Houſe of Commons ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Committee to draw up a charge of Treaſon againſt the ſaid Knights upon theſe ſeverall Votes, and preſent the ſame to the Houſe on Tuesday following, and ordered that Sir <hi>Iohn Stowell,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Winter</hi> ſhould be committed to the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Captaine <hi>Digby</hi> to the Gate-houſe, and the other to the Fleet, which was done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43473:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
